Hi, everyone.
I'm Claire.
And I'm Isaac.
And we are back.
We're back.
We are back for the new welcome
series, Meet Extreme Switching.
So why why switching, Isaac?
It's the stuff that made us famous.
I mean, we're a networking company.
We make switches and we do them
well.
We do do them well, and we're hoping
to explain this to you in five
episodes.
So does anyone need to know anything
about extreme switching before
doing this course?
Good question.
No, no, no.
There's there's no pre-requirements
for this, but this is going to
act as the pre-requisite for the
professional program.
So anybody who wants to know more
about extreme switching or do further
training, you have to pass an exam.
And you're going to tell us more.
Exactly.
So this does come with a certification
exam, which you guys know the drill.
Stay tuned to the end of episode
five.
We'll I'll be taking you through
how to gain access to that exam.
So for this episode, what have
we got coming up for episode one?
We don't assume that everybody
knows what a switch is, right?
So so we we talk we define what
it what is a switch.
We look at the history of the operating
system called EXR switch engine.
We look at how we got to all of
that.
And then we go a little bit more
into the hardware and show you
all the bits and pieces of what
a switch actually is.
So going to be interesting, yeah.
Yeah, a pretty jam-packed episode.
Are we ready to go?
Yeah.
We are.
Let's go.
So what exactly is a switch?
It could be unfair to assume that
everybody knows or has seen what
a switch is.
But in essence, a switch is a device,
a hardware device that connects
humans on the one side to resources
on the other side.
And those resources could be in
a corporate environment.
They could be a central printer.
They could be a security system.
They could be access control.
They could be connecting to an
HR system or a finance system.
All of those pieces need to be
connected together.
The switch is the device that enables
that.
In your home, you might also have
a switch.
It might look slightly different
to what a corporate switch looks
like.
Probably be a lot smaller, a lot
lighter, a lot less features.
But at its very simplest, it's
creating connections between humans,
devices, resources.
Extreme Networks as a company has
been around since 1996.
And in all that time, we've built
up a great reputation for making
fantastic hardware, fantastic switches.
But the thing we're most famous
for is this purple color that we've
painted our switches.
Of course, it doesn't add anything
to the functionality of the technology,
but it looks really great.
And if you've ever walked into
a data center that has our equipment,
you walk in and that purple is
so easy to identify.
Now as a networking company, switches
was the first thing that we've
done.
And of course, we've grown.
We now do wireless technology as
well.
And of course, we do management
software.
So we really do an end to end networking
solution.
In all that time, we've grown organically
and we've also made acquisitions.
We've bought in different types
of technologies and different companies
and taken their technologies, integrated
them into the stuff that we sell.
And today, we have a portfolio
that can compete with any of the
major players.
Of course, this is going to affect
the naming of our products.
As we've acquired technologies,
we've also acquired names that
can lead to a little bit of confusion
about the naming of our products.
And I'm going to explain the naming
specifically of our switches and
the operating systems that run
on these devices.
So take this journey with us.
It's a fascinating one as we go
into the world of switches.
You're going to hear me talk about
two operating systems throughout
this series.
And I'll use them interchangeably,
even though I'm going to try and
focus on one specifically.
I'm going to talk about EXOS and
I'm going to talk about switch
engine.
EXOS standing for extreme operating
system.
Every switch that you buy from
any manufacturer is going to have
an operating system on it up until
a point in time.
We used to refer to that operating
system as EXOS.
Then we introduced about two years,
two and a bit years ago, we introduced
the concept of something called
universal switches.
And the reason we did that is because
we had this great technology called
fabric.
And we used to make switches that
ran fabric.
And then we had other switches
that ran EXOS.
And you can imagine it means two
separate devices but essentially
the same physical switch.
So we brought these two operating
systems into a space where we could
give a customer a choice of which
one they wanted on the same physical
device, universal switching.
So you can now buy a device from
us, a purple switch.
That device has the ability to
run two operating systems on it,
either fabric.
And if you're interested in fabric,
the previous welcome series that
we did covers that in detail.
So you could run it as a fabric
switch or you could run it as EXOS.
Now when we introduced universal,
we stopped calling it EXOS.
We now call it switch engine.
It is the same operating system,
the same computer code, the same
everything.
It's just a name change.
So for the purposes of this series,
we will talk about switch engine.
For those of you who already have
our gear in place, that just translates
to EXOS.
That's all it is.
But let's talk about switch engine.
Why is it great?
Why the universal switch?
Why that technology?
Why would we introduce it?
Just think about existing customers
who have these networks in place.
They want to buy a new device.
They can buy it and it can fit
into the existing infrastructure.
If at some point in time they decide,
ooh, we'd like to be able to upgrade
to fabric because now we have multi-site,
a campus for example, it would
work a lot better in those environments.
Guess what?
If you have a universal device,
you can just bounce it again and
bring it up as a fabric switch.
You as a customer have a choice
which one you want to run.
And at any point in time without
having extra licenses or anything
like that, you can just switch
it to another operating system.
This gives you the option to design
a network, deploy a network, build
a network.
And when you need to re-deploy
it again.
Extreme universal switching and
the naming conventions that have
brought us here.
In our networking world, we use
terms, we use terminology that
oftentimes just makes sense to
us and not to people on the outside.
And if you hang around with networking
engineers for any significant period
of time, you're going to hear them
talk about layers.
You're going to hear them say things
like edge layer or aggregation
layer or core layer.
So they'll refer to those terms.
Firstly, let's talk about the edge
layer.
What that edge layer does is it
simply refers to the layer at which
humans, connections, devices connect
into their network.
So imagine you have a laptop and
you're walking around the office.
That laptop is probably connected
to the office using a wireless
connection.
So what is the first device?
What is the first network device
that your laptop connects to?
Well, it would be that access point.
That is the entrance into your
network.
That is an edge device.
If you're connecting, for example,
a printer into your network, then
your printer, your physical printer,
if it's one of those big office
ones, it would have a Ethernet
cable that runs all the way from
the back of the printer into a
switch in a data cabinet somewhere.
That switch, that's the edge of
your network, the first entry point
for the devices that you use to
connect to.
That can be a couple of hundred
of them in big enterprises, hundreds
of devices.
Or if you think about your home,
it could be one single device because
you plug your printer in, you plug
your TV in, you plug your Xbox
in.
All of those are going into the
edge device.
The next layer is what we call
the aggregation layer.
Let me use that example of edge
I spoke about when I said you could
have hundreds of these switches
or access points sitting on the
edge.
If you have all of these switches
and access points all with users
connected into them, hundreds,
maybe thousands, where does the
data that comes out of the switches
go to?
That goes to an aggregation switch.
An aggregation does exactly what
it says on the tin.
It aggregates the data.
It pulls in it, collects the data
from all those hundreds of switches
into a much more powerful switch.
It still has the Ethernet port.
It still has fiber optic ports.
It's got all of that but much more
high spec, much more high speed
capabilities.
The aggregation layer, the layer
behind the edge that sucks in all
of the data.
And then what do you find beyond
that?
You find the core, what we call
the core.
And that generally sucks up the
data from the aggregation layer
and traverses it, pushes it out
onto the internet.
The core layer.
So those are the terminologies.
That's the terminologies that network
engineers and networking companies
sell their products by.
They will sell you switches or
devices for the edge, devices for
aggregation layer, and devices
for the core.
Now that is simply being or that
has been for a long time the normal,
the classical approach to building
networks and and to naming networks.
There is a different approach as
well where the core is taken out
and you just have the edge and
you have the aggregation layer
because switches nowadays on the
aggregation layer are able and
capable to connect you.
Now certainly extreme network switches
do both layer two and layer three
connectivity, which means they
are able to get you directly onto
the internet.
So we have a classic model and
we have the more modern approach
to doing networking.
We've spoken a lot about the capabilities
that these switches have that the
operating system is able to do.
Let's look at a couple of switches.
We've brought two into the studio.
The first one is a Summit 480.
It's one of the older switches
that we have.
We'll start from left to right
and we'll work our way around the
switch.
So firstly on on the left hand
side over there, you'll see the
old connectors that we used to
use to to get into the console.
That would be what we call a serial
connector, a nine-pin connector.
Next to those, we have other ports.
You can see that they are blanked
similar to this and we'd use those
for stacking for example.
The next ports that we have over
there are the traditional RJ45
ports with different capacities
from one 100 mega bit per second,
a gig, 10 gig for example, 40 gig
if necessary.
Then you'd have over here these
ports again which are all blanked
out now.
The design around this is so that
the customer can choose how they
want to use these switches.
This gives the customer options.
So they can have these ports over
here, their SFP or SFP plus ports.
And they can contain different
types of fiber optic connectors.
To the right, we then have the
management ports, the switch management
ports, so the RJ45 and a USB connector
as well.
And finally, on this side, right
down the bottom on the right hand
side is the an indicator LED which
shows which member this is in a
stack.
Stacking allows you to take up
to eight of these and make them
behave as if they were a single
switch.
So that gives you that indication
of what the stacking is.
On the left side of the switch,
we have the mounting plates.
They of course can be moved forward
and backwards depending on how
deep you want to set them into
your rack.
And then of course these would
clip into your your calipers in
in in the back of the rack so that
you could pull it out and push
it back in when you need it to
do any changes.
The height of a switch is normally
measured in use or RU.
That simply signifies this is one
RU.
And you have most other switches
that also have that same height,
standard height, standard width
for any communications rack.
Moving to the back, we have a couple
of interesting connections over
here, a couple of interesting devices.
On this side over here, we have
the fan setup, the fans.
And you can see that we actually
have a blanking panel as well if
you wanted to purchase additional
redundant fans.
What do they look like?
Let me pull this out.
That's what the redundant fan little
unit looks like.
It just slides into there.
This one has three fans connected
to it.
The next one is the power supplies.
So here you see two different power
supplies.
Yes, you would physically have
two cables into there and they
would both be plugged in and running
at the same time.
So these are redundant power supplies.
They probably came with one and
then you can go and add another
one.
To remove that, you just click
on there and you pull that out.
So that is the redundant power
supply for one of these.
That's that's quite a that's quite
a big beast.
It's quite heavy, um really solidly
built.
And the reason that you would want
this is because it's not uncommon
that these devices have to be used
in mission-critical applications.
So the last thing you want is for
a switch like this carrying huge
amount of traffic to go down because
of a single power supply.
So generally speaking, any environment
that that requires a redundancy,
please purchase two or some of
them might even have more than
that power supplies.
If one goes down, the device is
still able to be powered from a
single one of these power supply
units.
And on this side, there's nothing
much to see.
It's just the same as the other
side.
And that's what one of the older
switches looks like.
So let's go now have a look at
what a newer universal switch,
the 5420 looks like.
So let's go again from left to
right on this 5420 series.
One of the neat new innovations
that they have on these universal
switches is this little paper tag.
When you pull it, you'll see it's
got a QR code on it, but it also
has the serial number of the device,
the MAC address of the device,
the part number of the device.
That's really really cool.
When you put that in, you have
two USB A ports over there.
You can plug in a a USB to update
for example the firmware if you
want to do it that way.
Or if you need to charge your phone,
you can just plug it into that
USB port.
Next up is the console and the
management ports, those top two
ports followed by underneath.
You have two blanked ports.
Now those are the stacking ports.
You can use them as one gigabit
or 10 gigabit stacking ports.
Remember you need special cables
for those.
Stacking, you can have up to eight
of these devices in a stack turning
this essentially into a single
switch with eight by 36 or 48 ports.
The next thing that you have over
here is the uplink ports.
Again, these uplink ports come
with SFP plus connectors or blanks.
And you would need to purchase
the connectors that you need for
whatever use case you need, short
distance, long distance, etc.
After that, you have Ethernet ports.
There are 48 Ethernet ports on
this particular switch.
Moving to the left of the switch,
you can see at this point we don't
yet have the mounting brackets
connected to this model over here.
But that's just in the packets
and we'll connect that up later.
Moving to the back of the switch,
unlike the previous switch we saw
a few minutes ago, this one doesn't
have redundant fans.
It's got three fans but none of
them are redundant.
Now it does have a built-in power
supply.
And then it has the blanking panel
if you wanted to add a second power
supply into this model.
Right, coming to this side, it's
exactly the same as the previous
side.
Nothing new to see.
And we'll bring this device around.
Really great piece of kit.
Not as heavy as the previous model,
shorter than the previous model
but again a one U rack model.
Now this model over here is actually
the 5420 F - 16 W 32 P 4 XE.
It's it's a it's a real tongue
twister but there's actually logic
in the name.
The 16 W means these 16 ports here
have eight or two dot three BT
power, meaning they are able to
offer 90 watts of power to power
up devices like security cameras
for example.
For the next 32 ports, you have
eight or two dot three AT power,
which is 30 watts of power.
And that's going to power up things
like security systems or even an
IP telephone on your desk.
The four XE means those four optical
ports that you have.
Just want to cover a few more points
with these switches.
And the first is the power.
Most switches will have AC power
on them but we do have a smaller
range of switches that have DC
power as well.
It's really a small range.
The ones that I've seen are desktop
switches, 16 port switches and
pretty silent switches.
So the fans don't come in until
a certain point in time.
So you have the ability to have
both of those options.
Another term that you will come
across is VIM VIM, versatile interface
module.
This switch also doesn't have that
but would be a component that would
plug into here that gives you the
option of having a different type
of connection method.
Some data centers use the concept
of hot and cold corridors to help
them extract the hot air out of
the data center as quickly as possible.
Some extreme network switches have
capabilities that will help data
centers manipulate that airflow.
Generally speaking, hot air is
is pushed out the back of these
switches.
Some of them, not this particular
model but some of them have the
ability for you to change the direction
of the airflow and to push it out
through the front.
So why would you want to change
the airflow?
Well, if you're in one of those
hot corridors, you really don't
want the airflow to be blown into
a cold corridor.
So you would reverse that and the
air would blow out the front into
that hot corridor where they can
then extract it to cool it down.
Blocked and unblocked switches.
What do they actually mean?
Well, a blocked switch is a switch
that does not have the capability
to push the maximum data rate right
across all of these ports full-time,
all the time, 24 hours a day.
It would block some of that.
An unblocked switch is a switch
like this one that is able to transmit
and receive data at the maximum
rate, one gigabit per second on
every single one of these ports.
In no way is this a comprehensive
end-to-end explanation of what
these switches are capable, what
the physical switches have in there.
But if you go to the extremenetworks.com
website and you go look for the
data sheets on these switches,
there you will find accurate information
on what the full capabilities of
the switch are.
In summary, we've looked at extreme,
our history, how our acquisitions
have affected our naming products.
We've spoken a little bit about
universal switching, what that
actually means, the benefits.
And then we got into describing
the different layers that network
engineers use when they talk about
networking products and technology
and approaches to the way we build
networks.
We then looked at hardware, actual
switch, and we went through all
the different components.
And hopefully that has kind of
brought some light if you if you
weren't aware of all the names
and all the components that has
made it easier to understand.
And so we've covered quite a lot
in this episode.
I look forward to seeing you on
the next one.